A Register of the A. V. (Anton Vasil'evich) Turkul papers
Hoover Institution Archives
A. V. (Anton Vasil'evich) Turkul papers
1917-1955
2007C51
Turkul, A. V. (Anton Vasil'evich)
1 microfilm reel (0.15 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The bulk of the papers of Turkel, a Major general in the White Russian army and commanding general of the Drozdovska´i`a strelkova´i`a divizi´i`a consist of correspondence with former comrades-in-arms relating to memories of the Civil War, as well as to émigré politics in the 1950s. The papers also include writings, printed matter, and photographs.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research
Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2007. This collection was loaned for microfilming, with the originals returned to the donor.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Chronology
1892 December 11 Born, Russia
1910 February 9 Entered military service, 56th Zhitomir Regiment
1914 October 20 Promoted to ensign
1916 September 19 Promoted to lieutenant
1918 January 8 Joins Col. M. G. Drozdovskii's unit in Romania
1919 May 14 Promoted to captain
1919 July 4 Promoted to colonel
1920 April 3 Promoted to major general
1920 August 7 Appointed commander of the Drozdovskii Division
1957 Died, Munich, Germany
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection of papers contains the service records of General Anton Vasil'evich Turkul covering the period of the Russian Civil War, in which Turkul commanded the Drozdovskii Division. The bulk of the papers consist of correspondence with former comrades-in-arms relating to memories of the Civil War, as well as to émigré politics in the 1950s. As editor of the journals Vlasovets and Dobrovolets, Turkul played a role in some of the political battles that took place among various groups, both military and civilian, in the emigration at that time (c. 1950-1957). Also included in the collection are thirty-eight prints of various scenes, from members of the Drozdovskii Division football club on Gallipoli in 1921 to anniversary banquets held in the 1930s-1960s. Some photographs are marked with names of participants on the reverse.
This collection was loaned for microfilming, with the originals returned to the donor.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into six series: Biographical File, Correspondence, Editor's File, Printed Matter, Photographs, Increment.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in Stanford University's online catalog.
Subjects
Russia (Territory under White armies, 1918-1920) Dobrovol'cheska´i`a armi´i`a. Drozdovska´i`a strelkova´i`a divizi´i`a.; Russia (Territory under White armies, 1918-1920 Armi´i`a--Officers.; Russians in foreign countries.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.
Related Material
Originals in possession of Boris Parr. This collection was loaned for microfilming, with the originals returned to the donor.
Container List
- Biographical File, 1917-1921 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Service records
- Correspondence, 1948-1961.
  Organized alphabetically by author and chronologically therein. Includes letters to Turkul's widow, Aleksandra Fedorovna
  - General – Congratulatory
    - Incoming, 1950-1955 (Folder 1: 2)
    - Outgoing, 1948-1952 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Unidentified, 1953-1957 and undated (Folder 1: 4)
  - All-Russian Liberation Committee (Sergei V. Iur'ev), 1954 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Anastasii, Metropolitan, 1955-1956 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Arkhangel'skii, Aleksei Petrovich, 1951-1955 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Averkii, Bishop, 1955 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Balabin, E., 1954 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Boiarintsev, Mitrofan Ivanovich (Folder 1: 10)
  - Cherepov, Vladimir Aleksandrovich, 1954-1955 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Dalakow (Dolokov), Ignatii Afanas'evich, 1957 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Damskii komitet Vlasovskogo ob"edineniia v S.A.S.Sh. (Fesenko, Galina Petrovna), 1954 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Donchenko, Ivan Zakharovich, 1955 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Dudetskii, Mr., 1955 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Erdeli, G., 1954 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Exil et Liberté, 1954 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Feodosii, Igumen, 1954-1955 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Fesenko, Galina Petrovna., See Damskii komitet Vlasovskogo ob"edineniia v S.A.S.Sh.
  - Fisher, Ekaterina Sergeevna, 1954-1955 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Fomin, Aleksandr Nikolaevich, 1955 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Glazenap, Igor' Leonidovich, 1955 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Gordeev, Andrei Dmitrievich, 1955 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Gribov, Ilarion Ivanovich, 1953-1955 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Iur'ev, Sergei V., See All-Russian Liberation Committee
  - Karlash, Sergei Matveevich., See Veterans Association of the General Drosdowsky Division
  - Kharzhevskii, Vladimir Grigor'evich, 1957 (Folder 1: 24)
  - Kholopov, Mr., 1955 (Folder 1: 25)
  - Khorolenko (Chorolenko), Andrei, 1954-1955 (Folder 1: 26)
  - Kingston, Mariia Sergeevna, 1955 (Folder 1: 27)
  - Kodimskii, Nikolai, 1954 (Folder 1: 28)
  - Kolisiuk, I., 1955 (Folder 1: 29)
  - Koltypin, Petr Nikolaevich, 1954 (Folder 1: 30)
  - Korol'kov, Nikolai Evdokimovich, 1955 (Folder 1: 31)
  - Kucherov, M., 1956 (Folder 1: 32)
  - Men'ko, Lev, 1955 (Folder 1: 33)
  - Mokin, Stepan, 1955 (Folder 1: 34)
  - Mutsenek-Martov, Vil'gel'm Karlovich, 1955 (Folder 1: 35)
  - Nemeshaev, N., 1954-1955 (Folder 1: 36)
  - Nilov, Sergei, 1955 (Folder 1: 37)
  - Nizovtsev, Lt. Col., 1955 (Folder 1: 38)
  - Orekhov, Vasilii Vasil'evich, 1955. (Folder 1: 39)
    Includes letter from N. Galai to Orekhov, undated
  - Orlov, G., 1957 (Folder 1: 40)
  - Penkin, A., undated (Folder 1: 41)
  - Polishchuk, S., 1954 (Folder 1: 42)
  - Protasovich, Viktor Aleksandrovich, 1951-1961 (Folder 1: 43)
  - Romar, Anatolii Filippovich, 1955 (Folder 1: 44)
  - Serdakovskii, Lev, 1955 (Folder 1: 45)
  - Sergeevskii, Boris Nikolaevich, 1954 (Folder 1: 46)
  - Sikorskii, P., 1955 (Folder 1: 47)
  - Sikorsky, Igor Ivanovich, 1954-1955 (Folder 1: 48)
  - Skarzhinskii, P., 1951-1953 (Folder 1: 49)
  - Tarsaidze, Aleksandr Georgievich, 1954 (Folder 1: 50)
  - Veterans Association of the General Drosdowsky Division (Karlash, Sergei Matveevich), 1951-1957 (Folder 1: 51)
  - Volkov, Mikhail Georgievich, 1955 (Folder 1: 52)
  - Zimninskii, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1955 (Folder 1: 53)
- Editor's File, undated. (Folder 1: 54)
  Includes miscellaneous manu- and typescripts (both Turkul's and those of others) for publication in Vlasovets or Dobrovolets
- Printed Matter, 1950-1954 and undated. (Folder 1: 55)
  Includes issues #1 and 2 of Vlasovets and other bulletins and clippings
- Photographs, 1921-1960s. (Folder 1: 56)
  Thirty-eight prints depicting A. V. Turkul, V. G. Kharzhevskii, and others (primarily officers of the Drozdovskii Division in emigration)
- Increment, 1936-1980
  - Biographical file
    - General, 1936-1957. (Folder 1: 57)
      Various documents
    - Letters of condolence, 1957. (Folder 1: 58)
      Sent to Turkul's widow, Aleksandra Fedorovna, and daughter, Tamara Antonovna
    - Obituaries, 1957-1967. (Folder 1: 59)
      Includes death notices, holograph notes and poems
    - Turkul, Aleksandra Fedorovna, 1957-1963 (Folder 1: 60)
      (letters to)
    - Turkul, Tamara Antonovna, 1980 (Folder 1: 61)
      (letter to)
  - Correspondence
    - General - Congratulatory, 1947-1961 (Folder 1: 62)
    - Mil'kovskii, 1955 (Folder 1: 63)
    - Veber, Lev Fedorovich, 1951 (Folder 1: 64)
  - Printed matter, 1948-1963 (Folder 1: 65)